A Guide to the Hospital Medical Ethics Committee Collection 1983-2000
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
Hospital Medical Ethics Committee Collection 1983-2000
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-11
The collection consists of 5 Hollinger boxes of processed materials.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by the Ethics Committee.
Biographical/Historical Information
In 1983, the University of Virginia Hospital Medical Policy Committee created the Hospital Medical Ethics Committee to develop policies relating to the issues of "Baby Doe" regulations, withdrawal of life support and right to die, brain death determination, and indigent care. The first meeting was on January 4, 1984, and its first chairman was Dr. Edward W. Hook.
Scope and Content
The Hospital Medical Ethics Committee Collection includes agendas, minutes, memos, policy drafts, articles and case studies related to the topics of discussion at committee meetings from its creation in 1983 to 2000. Highlights of the collection include discussions of the "Baby Doe" case, indigent access to care, the Natural Death Act, organ donation, HIV testing, confidentiality, development of the Code of Ethics, and the establishment of the Ethics Consultation Service (ECS) at the University of Virginia Hospital.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in chronological order, with the Organizational Ethics Subcommittee papers beginning at Box 5, folder 17.
Contents List
- Establishment of the Medical Ethics Committee and charges 1983 October 10 (Box-folder 01:01)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics and Cost 1984 January 4 (Box-folder 01:02)
- Meeting Agenda: Patient Bill of Rights, Baby Doe, fees 1984 February 21 (Box-folder 01:03)
- Meeting Agenda: Infant Care Review Committee, Baby Doe 1984 March 20 (Box-folder 01:04)
- Meeting Agenda: Right to Die, Infant Care review committee, finders fees for research subjects 1984 April 17 (Box-folder 01:05)
- Meeting Agenda: Infant Care review Committee, "finders fees" conflict of interest, right to die, indigent care 1984 May 15 (Box-folder 01:06)
- Meeting Agenda: Baby Doe, Natural Death Act, Indigent Care 1984 June 19 (Box-folder 01:07)
- Meeting Agenda: Clinical Consulting, Abortion fees for indigents 1984 September 27 (Box-folder 01:08)
- Meeting Agenda: Abortion policies, "finders fees" 1984 November 6 (Box-folder 01:09)
- Meeting Agenda: Composition, charges, responsibilities and accomplishments of Medical Ethics Committee (Special meeting with Congressional Aides) 1984 November 28 (Box-folder 01:10)
- Meeting Agenda: Baby Doe, Infant care, Abortion policies 1984 December 20 (Box-folder 01:11)
- Meeting Agenda: Abortion deposit policy 1985 January 22 (Box-folder 01:12)
- Meeting Agenda: Composition, charges, responsibilities and accomplishments of the Ethics committee (Special session with Congressional Aides) 1985 February 11 (Box-folder 01:13)
- Meeting Agenda: Abortion Deposit Policy 1985 February 26 (Box-folder 01:14)
- Meeting Agenda: Virginia Natural Death Act 1985 March 19 (Box-folder 01:15)
- Meeting Agenda: Virginia Natural Death Act 1985 April 23 (Box-folder 01:16)
- Meeting Agenda: Charges to Ethics Committee, Natural Death Act 1985 May 28 (Box-folder 01:17)
- Meeting Agenda: Natural Death Act, Patient information, "living wills" 1985 June 25 (Box-folder 01:18)
- Meeting Agenda: Baby Doe, staff education regarding Natural Death Act 1985 September 24 (Box-folder 01:19)
- Meeting Agenda: Proposed legislation regarding consent to medical treatment 1985 October 15 (Box-folder 01:20)
- Meeting Agenda: Guidelines for treatment decisions 1985 November 26 (Box-folder 01:21)
- Meeting Agenda: Discontinuation of Dialysis, Natural Death Act, living wills 1986 January 14 (Box-folder 01:22)
- Meeting Agenda: Treatment authorization, "Required request" for organ donation 1986 February 11 (Box-folder 01:23)
- Meeting Agenda: Ventilator management policies, DNR policy, Patient information about resuscitation 1986 May 28 (Box-folder 01:24)
- Meeting Agenda: case followup, "Required request," ventilator management, New York DNR case, Patient information on resuscitation 1986 June 25 (Box-folder 01:25)
- Meeting Agenda: Resuscitation and DNR issues 1986 October 14 (Box-folder 02:01)
- Meeting Agenda: Patient information, resuscitation issues 1986 November 10 (Box-folder 02:02)
- Meeting Agenda: Informed consent, confidentiality regarding testing for HIV antibody 1987 March 3 (Box-folder 02:03)
- Meeting Agenda: Testing for HIV antibody, Patient rights document revision, patient information about resuscitation and living wills 1987 June 29 (Box-folder 02:04)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics consultations, HIV antibody testing 1987 September 23 (Box-folder 02:05)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics Consultation Service, Determination of death 1987 November 18 (Box-folder 02:06)
- Meeting Agenda: HIV testing policies, Determining brain death, Ethics consultation subcommittee 1988 January 19 (Box-folder 02:07)
- Meeting Agenda: Committee on Determination of Brain Death, Ethics Consultation Service, Anencephalic infants as organ donors 1988 March 22 (Box-folder 02:08)
- Meeting Agenda: Housestaff manual, Ethics Consultation service, DNR policy, patient information 1988 April 21 (Box-folder 02:09)
- Meeting Agenda: Brain death determination, autopsies, Ethics Consultation service 1988 May 10 (Box-folder 02:10)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics Consultation service, Subcommittee on Anencephalic infants as organ donors, subcommittee on autopsies, DNR guidelines 1988 June 29 (Box-folder 02:11)
- Meeting Agenda: Use of cadavers in safety testing 1988 July 18 (Box-folder 02:12)
- Meeting Agenda: Consent for transfusion, subcommittee on Anencephalic infants as organ donors, subcommittee on the determination of brain death 1988 September 12 (Box-folder 02:13)
- Meeting Agenda: Guidelines for Brain Death determination, Natural Death Act brochure, Notification regarding HIV testing, Ethics consultation service 1988 October 17 (Box-folder 02:14)
- Meeting Agenda: Autopsy subcommittee, Ethics Consultation service, living will brochure, notification about HIV testing 1988 November 21 (Box-folder 02:15)
- Meeting Agenda: Autopsy consent form, Ethics Consultation service, DNR policy 1988 December 19 (Box-folder 02:16)
- Meeting Agenda: Identification of students involved in patient care, Ethics Consultation service, DNR policy draft 1989 January 16 (Box-folder 02:17)
- Meeting Agenda: Evaluation of Ethics Committee, Guardianship issues, Identification of students involved in patient care, autopsy consent, DNR policy 1989 February 20 (Box-folder 02:18)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics Consultation Service, identification of medical students, Information for hospital patients, substance abuse and pregnancy 1989 April 17 (Box-folder 02:19)
- Meeting Agenda: Anencephalic infants as organ donors presentation, HIV seroprevalence study, DNR policy 1989 May 22 (Box-folder 02:20)
- Meeting Agenda: HIV seroprevalence study, Evaluation of Ethics consultations, DNR policy 1989 June 19 (Box-folder 03:01)
- Meeting Agenda: "Practices of Written and Oral Consent" presentation, Anencephalic infants as organ donors, Donor oocyte program, living will 1989 September 25 (Box-folder 03:02)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics Consultation Service, patient information brochures 1989 October 16 (Box-folder 03:03)
- Meeting Agenda: Patient Rights to self-determination Bill, CPR as medical therapy 1989 November 20 (Box-folder 03:04)
- Meeting Agenda: Right to Die, Ethics Consultation Service, Sister egg donors, smoking privileges for hospice patients 1989 December 18 (Box-folder 03:05)
- Meeting Agenda: Hospital living will policy, DNR central registry, Ethics Consultation service, "Code of Ethics" from UVA Hospital bylaws 1990 January 15 (Box-folder 03:06)
- Meeting Agenda: Living Will brochure, Non-physicians with clinical appointments conflict of interest, Ethics Consultation service 1990 February 19 (Box-folder 03:07)
- Meeting Agenda: Treatment of HIV patients, Research using aborted fetal tissue 1990 March 19 (Box-folder 03:08)
- Meeting Agenda: Patient Care brochure, Ethics Consultation service, Confidentiality in use of patient information for teaching 1990 April 16 (Box-folder 03:09)
- Meeting Agenda: Subcommittee on confidentiality issues, Ethical decision-making involving MICU patients, Ethics Consultation service 1990 May 21 (Box-folder 03:10)
- Meeting Agenda: Confidentiality Medical Policy, Donor eggs from friends, Ethics Consultation service 1990 June 18 (Box-folder 03:11)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics Consultation Service Natural Death Act case 1990 July 5 (Box-folder 03:12)
- Meeting Agenda: Patient Self-determination Act, Patient handbook, abortion policy, Ethics Consultation service 1990 September 17 (Box-folder 03:13)
- Meeting Agenda: Abortion policy, Ethics consultation service evaluation survey 1990 October 15 (Box-folder 03:14)
- Meeting Agenda: Living will education, Ethics committee confidentiality, Ethics Consultation service 1990 November 19 (Box-folder 03:15)
- Meeting Agenda: Confidentiality policy, Living will education, Ethics Consultation service survey, Access to care 1990 December 17 (Box-folder 03:16)
- Meeting Agenda: Living Will education, DNR and intra-hospital transfers, Indigent care and budget cuts, Ethics Consultation service 1991 January 21 (Box-folder 03:17)
- Meeting Agenda: Policy on Indigent care, Ethics Consultation service survey, Ethics Consultation service 1991 February 18 (Box-folder 03:18)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics Consultation service, Living wills, Access to health care 1991 March 18 (Box-folder 03:19)
- Meeting Agenda: Access to health care, Ethics Consultation service, Confidentiality policy 1991 April 15 (Box-folder 03:20)
- Meeting Agenda: Confidentiality of Student health records, subcommittee on Advance directives, Access to health care, Ethics Consultation service 1991 May 20 (Box-folder 04:01)
- Meeting Agenda: Student health audit, Ethics Consultation service survey, Access to health care, Ethics Consultation service 1991 June 17 (Box-folder 04:02)
- Meeting Agenda: Access to health care, Ethics Consultation service survey, Student Health Audit, Ethics Consultation service 1991 July 15 (Box-folder 04:03)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics Consultation service survey, Confidentiality and patient release, DNR policy, Confidentiality policy in cafeteria, Ethics education, Ethics Consultation service 1991 September 16 (Box-folder 04:04)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics Consultation service survey, DNR orders during radiology and anesthesiology procedures, Ethics Consultation Service, Patient Self-Determination Act 1991 October 21 (Box-folder 04:05)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics Consultation Service survey, DNR orders during radiology and anesthesiology procedures, Patient Self-Determination Act, Colloquy for State Appellate Judges, Ethics Consultation Service 1991 November 18 (Box-folder 04:06)
- Meeting Agenda: DNR, Ethics Consultation Service, Ethics Consultation Service survey, Evaluation of Subcommittee of Ethics Consultation Service 1991 December 16 (Box-folder 04:07)
- Meeting Agenda: Suspension of DNR orders, DNR policy revision, Ethics Consultation Service survey, Ethics Consultation Service 1992 January 20 (Box-folder 04:08)
- Meeting Agenda: DNR policy revisions, Patient Self-determination Act, Ethics Consultation Service 1992 February 17 (Box-folder 04:09)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics Consultation Serves Survey results 1992 March 16 (Box-folder 04:10)
- Meeting Agenda: Indigent organ transplants, Ethics Consultation Service, DNR policy 1992 May 18 (Box-folder 04:11)
- Meeting Agenda: Access to transplants by indigents, Pain management, Ethics Consultation Service 1992 June 15 (Box-folder 04:12)
- Meeting Agenda: Advance Directives policy changes, Ethics Consultation service final evaluation, DNR policy changes, Ethics Consultation Service 1992 September 21 (Box-folder 04:13)
- Meeting Agenda: Virginia Organ Procurement Agency presentation, DNR policy, Ethics Consultation Policy, Ethics Consultation Service 1992 November 16 (Box-folder 04:14)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics consultation policy, CPR survival, Ethics Consultation service 1992 December 21 (Box-folder 04:15)
- Meeting Agenda: Infant Brain death policy, DNR policy, Education on Advance Directives, Ethics Consultation Service 1993 January 18 (Box-folder 04:16)
- Meeting Agenda: Advance Directives, Mandatory reassessment of DNR orders, Ethics Consultation Service, Brain Death policy revision 1993 February 15 (Box-folder 04:17)
- Meeting Agenda: Infant Brain Death policy, Patient Self-determination Act Compliance Evaluation, Ethics Consultation Service, DNR policy revision, EMS-DNR policy, Ethics Consultation Service evaluation 1993 April 19 (Box-folder 04:18)
- Palliative and Terminal Care research initiative, Humanities and Caring for terminally ill patients, Virginia's Health Care Decision Act of 1992, DNR orders problems and policies, Withdrawing treatment, Advance Directives 1993 May 10 (Box-folder 04:19)
- Meeting Agenda: Neonatal Brain Death Policy, DNR policy revisions, Advance Directives Committee 1993 May 17 (Box-folder 04:20)
- Meeting Agenda: Formation of Executive Committee, formation of subcommittee on Ethics Education, Health Care Ethics forum 1994 January 17 (Box-folder 04:21)
- Meeting Agenda: Liver lobe transplantation, Education Subcommittee, Ethics Consultation Service 1994 February 21 (Box-folder 04:22)
- Decision-making policy in non-capable pregnant patients 1994 April 11 (Box-folder 04:23)
- Revised Confidentiality policy 1994 May 26 (Box-folder 04:24)
- Drug Dosages and terminally ill patients 1994 June 13 (Box-folder 04:25)
- Forgoing Treatment policy 1995 July 20 (Box-folder 04:26)
- Meeting Agenda: Therapeutic effects of Cannabis 1995 October 16 (Box-folder 04:27)
- Meeting Agenda: Brain Death policy, Education subcommittee 1996 January 15 (Box-folder 04:28)
- Ethics Consultation Policy 1996 February 27 (Box-folder 04:29)
- "Revised Guidelines for the Determination of Brain Death" 1996 March 8 (Box-folder 04:30)
- Subcommittee to Revise the Advance Directives policy 1996 March 18 (Box-folder 05:01)
- Meeting Agenda: Organizational Ethics policy, Patient Brochure 1996 May 20 (Box-folder 05:02)
- Ethics Consultation Policy changes 1996 June 5 (Box-folder 05:03)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics Consultation Service, Education Program, Organizational code of ethics 1996 October 25 (Box-folder 05:04)
- Meeting Agenda: Blood Bank and C-J disease, organizational code of ethics, Awareness of activities 1996 November 18 (Box-folder 05:05)
- Meeting Agenda: Transfusion and C-J disease, community ethics education, informed consent 1997 January 31 (Box-folder 05:06)
- Meeting Agenda: Informed consent, code of ethics, surrogate decision-makers, patient management 1997 February 24 (Box-folder 05:07)
- Meeting Agenda: Early Identification of ICU patient surrogates, Ethics Education 1997 March 28 (Box-folder 05:08)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics Education Liaisons, Notification of at-risk patients, DNR policy, resuscitation of near-viable infants 1997 April 28 (Box-folder 05:09)
- Meeting Agenda: Code of ethics, Albumen shortage, DNR problems 1997 June 30 (Box-folder 05:10)
- Resources in short supply and their distribution 1997 July 18 (Box-folder 05:11)
- Meeting Agenda: "Forgoing Treatment" policy, ethics education liaisons 1997 September 22 (Box-folder 05:12)
- Meeting Agenda: Code of physician ethics, Patient rights and responsibilities 1998 October 19 (Box-folder 05:13)
- Meeting Agenda: Living donor liver transplantation, confidentiality, code of ethics 1998 October 30 (Box-folder 05:14)
- Meeting Agenda: "Forgoing Treatment" policy, partial liver transplantation 1998 November 16 (Box-folder 05:15)
- Meeting Agenda: "Mailbox in-service" education, Medical policies 1999 April 16 (Box-folder 05:16)
- Meeting Agenda: Establishment of Organizational Ethics Subcommittee, code of ethics 1996 October 28 (Box-folder 05:17)
- Meeting Agenda: UVA Medical Center Code of Ethics, confidentiality of computerized patient records 1996 November 18 (Box-folder 05:18)
- Meeting Agenda: Code of Ethics, confidentiality 1996 December 16 (Box-folder 05:19)
- Meeting Agenda: Code of Ethics, surrogate decision-makers 1997 January 20 (Box-folder 05:20)
- Meeting Agenda: Code of Ethics, managed care 1997 February 10 (Box-folder 05:21)
- Meeting Agenda: Patient care, Code of Ethics 1997 March 17 (Box-folder 05:22)
- Meeting Agenda: Code of Ethics 1997 April 28 (Box-folder 05:23)
- Meeting Agenda: Code of Ethics 1997 June 2 (Box-folder 05:24)
- Meeting Agenda: Confidentiality of genetic testing, institutional ethics education 1997 July 21 (Box-folder 05:25)
- Meeting Agenda: Code of Ethics scenarios, hospital costs for patients 1997 October 20 (Box-folder 05:26)
- Meeting Agenda: Compendium of costs 1997 November 10 (Box-folder 05:27)
- Meeting Agenda: Compendium of costs, Physicians code of ethics, Physicians treating family members 1997 December 15 (Box-folder 05:28)
- Meeting Agenda: Genetic testing confidentiality 1998 January 19 (Box-folder 05:29)
- Meeting Agenda: Pharmacy costs 1998 February 16 (Box-folder 05:30)
- Meeting Agenda: Compendium of costs, genetic services 1998 March 16 (Box-folder 05:31)
- Meeting Agenda: Creation of Genetic Services Subcommittee 1998 April 20 (Box-folder 05:32)
- Meeting Agenda: Expectations of Behavior 1998 June 15 (Box-folder 05:33)
- Meeting Agenda: Physicians responsibility, physicians code of ethics 1998 October 9 (Box-folder 05:34)
- Meeting Agenda: Code of Ethics 1998 December 11 (Box-folder 05:35)
- Meeting Agenda: Code of Ethics 1999 January 8 (Box-folder 05:36)
- Meeting Agenda: Corporate compliance 1999 March 12 (Box-folder 05:37)
- Meeting Agenda: Compendium of costs, Code of Ethics for Health Care Professionals 1999 May 14 (Box-folder 05:38)
- "Physician relationship to patients, other physicians, systems of care, and society" 1999 June 8 (Box-folder 05:39)
- Meeting Agenda: Health System Corporate Compliance 1999 September 10 (Box-folder 05:40)
- Meeting Agenda: Code of Ethics 1999 October 8 (Box-folder 05:41)
- Meeting Agenda: Code of Ethics, Standards of Business Conduct 1999 November 10 (Box-folder 05:42)
- Meeting Agenda: Ethics case studies, Privacy/Confidentiality 2000 January 14 (Box-folder 05:43)
- Meeting Agenda: Confidentiality and facilities planning 2000 February 11 (Box-folder 05:44)
- Meeting Agenda: Confidentiality/Privacy-sensitive Environment planning 2000 March 17 (Box-folder 05:45)
- Meeting Agenda: Confidentiality, Compendium of costs 2000 April 14 (Box-folder 05:46)
- Meeting Agenda: Confidentiality, Code of Ethics, Compliance Code of Conduct 2000 May 12 (Box-folder 05:47)
- Meeting Agenda: Code of Ethics 2000 September 8 (Box-folder 05:48)
- Meeting Agenda: Conflict of Interest, Code of Ethics and Compliance 2000 November 10 (Box-folder 05:49)